let's find the derivative of tangent 4X
using the first principle's definition
of derivatives let's start by defining
our function let F ofx = tangent 4X
therefore f of x + H = tangent of 4 * x
+ H now let's recall the definition of a
derivative the derivative of f ofx is
equal to the Limit as h approaches Z of
f ofx + H - F ofx all divid H let's
substitute our function into this
definition the derivative of tangent 4X
equals the limit as H approaches Z of
tangent of 4 * x + H - Tang 4X all
divided H now let's rewrite tangent in
terms of s over cosine this gives us the
limit as H approaches Z of s 4x + h/
cosine of 4x + H - sin 4X cosine 4X all
divided by H to subtract these fractions
we need a common denominator multiplying
both numerator and denominator of each
fraction by the denominator of the other
gives us this expression the numerator
is the S of the difference of angles
formula this simplifies to S of 48 H in
the numerator let's factor out the four
from the sign term this gives us 4 * the
limit as H approaches 0 of sin 4 H over
4 H divided by the product of the
cosiness now we can split this into two
limits the limit of sin 4 H over 4 H as
H approaches 0 = 1 and the limit of cine
4x + H as H approaches 0 = cosine 4X
this simplifies to 4 over cine 4X which
equal 4 secant 4X and that's our final
answer to verify this result we could
graph tangent 4X and it's derivative to
see that the derivative is indeed
steepest at the same points where
tangent 4X has its steepest slopes